A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs, Series Q FA326
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs, Series Q
1896-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Standard Oil Company
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller Foundation
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
China Medical Board (U.S)
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Sealantic Fund, New York
Spelman Fund
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Davison Fund
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller family
Rockefeller, Winthrop
International Education Board
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Spelman family
Rockefeller, David
FA326
48 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into seven sections:
Foreign Policy, Institute of Pacific Relations, National Defense, Post-War Reconstruction, Peace Plans, War Relief, National War Fund.
Scope and Contents note
The World Affairs series reflects the Rockefeller family's contributions toward national defense and international relations. The series is divided into seven sections: Foreign Policy, including the Foreign Policy Association and the Council on Foreign Relations; Institute of Pacific Relations; National Defense, which includes material on war preparedness, veteran's organizations, civil defense, the Commander Byrd expeditions and the New York City Airport Authority; Post-War Reconstruction; Peace Plans, which contains material on peace organizations, the League of Nations and the United Nations (including material on John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gift of the site for the United Nations headquarters); War Relief; and National War Fund.
The family members who figure most prominently in the papers are John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, and David Rockefeller. John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, and Mary French Rockefeller also appear.
When members of the family were active in an organization, for example the Council on Foreign Relations, the files reflect that activity. For the most part, however, correspondence is unsolicited appeals for donations handled by members of the 5600 office staff.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Philanthropy; Public health administration; Public policy; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Arts; Business; Business enterprises, Foreign; Philanthropy -- United States; Capital investments; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; Charities -- Investments; Child welfare; Civic improvement; International cooperation; International economic relations; International education; International relations; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Medical care; Maternal health services; Medical research; Medical education; New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); Performing arts; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Public health; Prohibition; Urban renewal; Urban policy; World War II; World War I; State governments -- United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; United States; Travel; Religion; Public welfare; Restoration and conservation; Religious institutions; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Health insurance; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Folk art; Government policy; Economic policy; Economics; Education; Education -- United States; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Art; Economic development; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Standard Oil Company; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, John D.; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller Center; Rockefeller Foundation; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth); Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Sealantic Fund, New York; Spelman Fund; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Davison Fund; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller family; Rockefeller, Winthrop; International Education Board; Mauze, Abby Rockefeller; Spelman family; Rockefeller, David
- Foreign Policy
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association, 1925-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Invitations, requests for donations and advice. Offers of information. Question of Foreign Policy Association "leftism". John D. Rockefeller, Jr. a member, John D. Rockefeller 3rd a member of the board until 1961. Organizational retrenchment in 1961. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Thomas B. Appleget, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller, John W. Nason.
    File Plan note
    187
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association, 1925-1957 (Box 1, Folder 0001A)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 0002A)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Opium Committee, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Bureau of Social Hygiene contributes to studies of international control of opium trade. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Headline Books, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd contributes $700 to cost of newstand sale of books. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Radio Program - J. G. McDonald, 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes to radio series on world affairs given by J. G. McDonald of the Foreign Policy Association (FPA). Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, J. G. McDonald.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Pledge June 14, 1929, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Family contributions to work of Association. Membership dues. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions for research work. Pledges separated: 1929, 1932, 1933, 1934. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Laurance Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Pledge June 24, 1932 (Contributions), 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Pledge June 15, 1933 (Contributions), 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Pledge May 29, 1934 (Contributions), 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - Fund Raising, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's advice requested in procedures of fund raising campaign. Refused to act as chairman, assisted in contacting possible contributors. Campaigns not entirely successful. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel, John W. Nason.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - World Affairs Center for the United States (Previously Service Bureau for World Affairs), April 1955-January 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - World Affairs Center for the United States (Previously Service Bureau for World Affairs), February 1956-July 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - World Affairs Center for the United States, April 1957-November 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Formerly the Foreign Policy Association Service Bureau for World Affairs. Name changed to World Affairs Center in 1957. Formation of organization to provide information on international affairs. Financing organization. Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributes $50,000 annually. Proposal to extend minority group participation in world affairs. Progress reports. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John W. Nason, Charles P. Noyes, Dana S. Creel, Richard S. Winslow.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - World Affairs Center for the United States, April 1959-December 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - John D. Rockefeller 3rd
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's interest. Named director 1954. Subversive accusations; answers. Requests for John D. Rockefeller 3rd's participation. 40th anniversary. Activities. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Brooks Emeny, John W. Nason.
    - October 1930-February 1952 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - May 1952-December 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1948-January 1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - February 1955-March 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - September 1955-April 1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - May 1956-December 1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - January 1958-August 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - September 1958-November 1958 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - December 1958-October 1959 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - November 1959-July 1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - World Affairs Center - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Answer to attack by Georgia Post of American Legion. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's annual contribution. $5,000 for equipment in 1952. Other large gifts, $25,000 approximately in 1958. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John W. Nason.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - World Affairs Center - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1930-1961 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Letters of Appeal, April 1954-May 1956 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd wrote letters to leading foundations, corporations and individuals appealing for contributions to the Foreign Policy Association. John D. Rockefeller 3rd defends staff member from subversion charge. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Policy Association - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Letters of Appeal, June 1956-June 1960 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations, March 1919-April 1946 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s support. Reports. Memorial to Edwin F. Gay. Contributions from the boys toward general support. Harold Pratt House. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., George S. Franklin.
    187.1
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations, May 1946-January 1951 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations, February 1951-August 1961 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    General note
    DR material removed to Folder 31A.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations, February 1951-August 1961 (Box 4, Folder 0031A)
    David Rockefeller's contribution. Contributions from the boys toward general support.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - David Rockefeller Contributions, 1944-1961 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    David Rockefeller a member of library committee. Suggestions for membership in Council. Contributions 1944-1962 -- ranged between $5,000 and $20,000 per year.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - David Rockefeller Correspondence, 1946-1961 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Contributions, 1934-1962 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Gifts ranged from small $15 item to $1,000 annually for general purposes. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, April 1930-November 1949 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's interest in Far East relations. Dinners, presideing over meetings. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, George S. Franklin, Hamilton J. Armstrong.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, January 1950-October 1953 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, November 1953-January 1958 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, April 1958-November 1961 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence - Address, April 1954 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    By John D. Rockefeller 3rd. No copy here.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - American Cultural Relations with Japan, November 1952-December 1952 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's participation in study group, chairman. Discussion, meeting reports. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Robert S. Schwantes.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - American Cultural Relations with Japan, December 1952-March 1953 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - American Cultural Relations with Japan, March 1930-May 1956 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - America-Burma Study Group, June 1957-January 1958 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd served as chairman of special study group. F. N. Trager did basic research. Study papers and minutes of discussion sessions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, F. N. Trager, Dean Rusk.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - America-Burma Study Group, February 1958-March 1958 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - America-Burma Study Group, April 1958 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - America-Burma Study Group, May 1958-December 1958 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Southeast Asia Study Group, November 1953-April 1954 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd participated in Council's study group on Southeast Asia. Covered Burma, Indonesia, Laos, Cambodia and Viet Nam. Background papers, history of the region. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Southeast Asia Study Group, May 1954-December 1954 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Southeast Asia Study Group, January 1955-March 1956 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - 1959 Study Group on United States Policy in Southeast Asia, June 1959-March 1960 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - 1959 Study Group on United States Policy in Southeast Asia, April 1960-October 1960 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Indo-China, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    Reports on discussions. John D. Rockefeller 3rd attended some meetings. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Japan-American Economic Relations Study Group, June 1958-January 1959 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    Reports. John D. Rockefeller 3rd participation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Gus Maffry.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Japan-American Economic Relations Study Group, February 1959-May 1959 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) Study Group, March 1954-July 1954 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd participation. Study papers. Discussion digest. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) Study Group, September 1954-January 1955 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Foreign Policy - Council on Foreign Relations - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) Study Group, February 1955-May 1956 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Foreign Policy - Foreign Affairs Council - Cleveland, 1938-1944 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made small contribution to Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd interested in work. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Brooks Emeny.
    187.2
  - Foreign Policy - Council for Inter-American Cooperation, Inc., May 1944-November 1946 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    Organized by Nelson A. Rockefeller to promote Inter-American cooperation through exchange of people ideas. Continued in operation after Nelson A. Rockefeller interest and support ceased. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Victor Borella, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John E. Lockwood.
    187.3
  - Foreign Policy - Council for Inter-American Cooperation, Inc., December 1946-June 1956 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Foreign Policy - Council for Inter-American Cooperation, Inc. - Contributions, 1944-1956 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller made contributions in 1944 and 1956.
- Institute of Pacific Relations
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - American Institute of Pacific Relations